We continue the series about reinforcement learning in animation and last time we've
seen how we could have a discrete state space and a discrete value function.
This time we will see how we could have a continuous state space.
Hi, I'm Jerome and today's paper is the new optimal character animation with continuous
control, a paper from 2007.
As usual for that paper, what I would do is import all the libraries I need and then
Then I will import my character, I will import different measures that I will display, and
the targets and that kind of stuff.
And this time, it's a bit different instead of importing just an animation coming from
LaFanne.
I already pre-sliced the animation because the way this paper works, it expects to have
a bunch of clips of animations that are represented this way.
So you start at the crossing phase, then you get the contact, then you get the next crossing
and then the next contact and the last crossing.
And that is considered for them as one clip.
You get the clip in, it goes from the first crossing to the middle crossing, and then
the clip out is the other part.
So I will need to have that information.
So what I've done is that I've already picked a few animations that are needed and I've
already set up the proper timing of when is the crossing, when is the contact and all
that kind of stuff.
So for instance, I've loaded all of those and if I display the first animation I have,
it is this one and that's the animation I will be using and slicing as clips, but I've
already pre-processed all the informations of when those contacts happen, right?
So what I need to do is to build the motion model the same way as they've done it here,
really splitting the clips with knowing if it's the left foot starts, when is the contact and so on.
And so what I have is this, I get a bunch of clips, all the informations were already in,
so I know how many clips I have that start with the left foot, I know how many clips I have that
I start with the right foot.
That's all the clip count I have.
So I have 36 foot steps basically.
And I will compute that as being a set of animations,
a set of clips.
So I get the cut onion and positions for each of my clips
and the different timing.
And so I have as many clip count as I have,
as many frames I have, the bone counts
and the cut onions and so on and so on.
So now clip Q, clip P will be a bunch of clips animations.
And so this is recomputing the route
to realign every time all the clips to start at zero zero.
And that's the function to compute those clips.
So really just taking the ranges that I've decided
and cutting all the animations, copy pasting
and realigning everything every time.
And that's what I'm doing.
hey, I now have inside of all my clips and formations,
I get all the different clips,
all the different timings for each of those clips.
Now, what is interesting in this model
is that they decided to work without any IK,
any post-process, so they need to make sure
that when you blend the clips together,
you don't need to post-process with the IKs.
And the way they've done it is they decided to say,
Basically, every time you try to blend an animation,
so that's a clip here, the A is a clip,
so you get the A in, A out.
You will have the contact points,
so that's where we decide that we have the contact.
And you basically align the two clips,
the two clips together at that contact time.
So that's what you do here.
If I need to blend between clip A to clip B,
First thing you do is that you move clip B so the foot that is in contact would not move
and you realign the entire animations relative to that. So every time you will blend basically
you're sure that the foot that is in contact with the ground would not slide because you moved the
entire animation relative to the contact positions. So what I would do is that I will compute all those
contact position depending on the timing so I know in my timings when is the contact and I
compute the positions of my foot every time I have a contact so that's what I'm doing here in
this function. The way I do it is I take the the ankle and the toe and I project that on the ground
and that represents the orientation of the position, the orientation of the foot and how I would want
to align everything together. So now if I want to display all the different clips I have, I can see
the different contact positions and I see the the clip motions that I have
and when I pass the animation I don't have any more animation. So that represents one clip
and I can go and then can pick any other clips. That's another steps. Let's see if I get something
a bit different. One other steps and all that kind of stuff.
And I get every time the contact with the two feet and so I will be able to blend that properly.
So what we do is that we see how we could actually blend the animations together and see how it
works. So what I have is I have a player again that's allowed me to keep playing animations
depending on the states I'm in and a clip itself is this information he knows the the clip idea I
have, he knows which frame I'm actually playing and then he will also know when I need to start
playing because if you see here for instance when I need to go from B to C because of the contact
happening only at the end only blend during this timing and that's me that I will only start to
to blend coming from this animation, this frame in, out.
But I might also,
is that an example why you don't start at the beginning?
But you might also not start at the beginning of in,
depending on how you align everything.
So that's struck me when I need to start
to play my animations.
I start to blend.
That's tell me when I need to start
to play the current animations.
that says how many time or how long is the blend.
So all of that is computed when I said,
I have a clip and I want you to align to another clip.
That's the align function, what it's doing.
And then I get the tick to say play one frame.
And the player itself will always have one current clip
that it's playing and he will have the informations
of the next clip that he wants to play.
He will make sure that he aligns them
and then check if it needs to play
or if it needs to blend and that kind of stuff.
So that's what the player would do.
When it ticks, it ticks both and do the blending
and everything that I need to do.
So if I put that in use, what I will have is this.
So I get the red skeleton is the current clip.
The green skeleton is what I will play after
and I could let it play basically anything.
So what I'm doing now is I just pick randomly
any clip to play, each choose,
which was the next clip to play.
You could see that you can always blend.
So some blends are terrible,
some blends are fairly good,
depending on how lucky you are when you pick your next clip.
But that's how the animations is perfectly able to blend.
Let's restart it.
Blend all those animations
and make sure that your foot is never sliding.
You don't need any post-IK solver or anything.
This is just playing animations and blending them together.
Now, we've seen how basically that's
how the motion database is done.
So it's a bunch of clips you could play.
You could connect those clips together.
you can blend them and it works properly.
Now we do need to decide how we want to control this
and how we will be able to interact with the character,
not picking any stuff randomly.
And so in the control part,
what we have, they have really big state space
with a lot of different values and that kind of stuff.
But basically what they say in the paper is that they regrouped everything here in the paper,
but they've never treated the state space as being that massive thing that can do everything.
They've just learned different controllers on different parts of the state space and that kind of stuff.
So that's what I would do also.
I would simplify the paper and treat only one case and work from there.
And the first thing I would do is because if I jump a bit in advance,
the traditional thing that you will have to make sure that is trying to see if the next animations
you want to play is coherent physically. So is the animation close together? Is the velocity
close? And that will be the cost of what they call the physics cost that you could see here.
So, that's the physics cost is how much, well, is how good is the transition going from clip A to clip B, is it good or bad.
So, that we could pre-compute because computing in every time will be losing resources.
What we could do is just compute in advance the cost of that transition for every possible transitions we can have.
have. So this is what I will compute here. Basically what I'm doing is I'm taking one clip,
I'm taking one clip, I realign that clip to when the contact happens,
and then I go through all the other clips and align all the other clips. And when I do this,
then I will start to compute the distances between every bones for all the frame during the blending.
So let's give me basically the cost, how close both clips are in the trajectories for every bones
during all the blends. So I pre-compute that cost and so that's what the physics cost will be
here and that's the interesting stuff to compute for the physics cost.
And I will let it pre-compute all of those informations for me.
It does it for the 36 clips with all the 36 possibilities.
And I will start to also pre-compute a bunch of other informations that are interesting in my case.
And it's to pre-compute what will be the next states as soon as I take one of the transitions.
So if you look at the control, what you could see is that you get the function from being
in one specific state and going into a different clips and how you do compute the new states.
So what is the states?
I will not go through all of those variables in my case.
I would only learn the one that I'm interested in.
And C basically is the clip I'm playing.
X and Z are the position of my character
on the ground plane.
And theta is the orientation of my character
And I will basically only work with those one.
And that will represent a state space for me.
That represents one state.
So the clip, the X position, the Z positions,
and the theta orientation.
That represents a state.
And then if you try to do a transition between X
and going to a different clip,
this is the formula that give you
to find the new states that will be,
so X prime will be the new states.
And the new states will be the new clip, C prime.
And then there will be X plus the cosine of theta
of delta x, delta minus sin theta of delta z.
And how do you compute delta x and delta z and delta theta?
It is the blending algorithm
that gives you that information.
So basically, all the stuff that compute
when I do clip A and align to clip B
and detect how much time I have to blend,
where is the contact and all that kind of stuff.
That's what gives me the delta x, the delta z
and the delta delta theta.
It's really depending on each clip
and how you blend the clips together.
So I can, at the same times,
I'm aligning everything to compute the physics cost.
I can use that information to compute the delta x
or much because I've realigned clip A
and then I could check where clip B arrive in X, Z, and theta.
And so I pre-compute delta X, delta Z, and delta theta.
So I have all the information I can use.
I get all the deltas, I get the physics costs.
I can start to check and work with all the clips.
Now, I would divide the physics costs by the mean.
by the mean. So I get something, I don't get massive numbers, I get something that stays
between zero and two, three depending. So it's all normalizing the physics costs.
And the last thing I would do, I would say that I know that I have a bunch of clips that
start with the left foot first, and I have a bunch of clips that start with the right
foot first and basically I make sure that the the cost of playing the wrong foot is extremely high
basically just making sure that I would never try to play a clip on the wrong foot and that's how
I'm doing it here it's just I make a really big cost of going into the wrong clip. The paper was
doing something different the paper was basically saying that every clips could blend with every clips
and if it's a clip with the left foot that want to play and blend toward another clip left foot
they were mirroring the clip. But I didn't want to make the video too complex because you need
to track which foot is in front. There is a lot of mathematics at the end where you will start to
You need to flip all the mathematics
because you are on the mirror and animations,
that kind of stuff.
And it was easy in my case to just say,
don't deal with the mirroring,
just make sure that we will never play the wrong animation.
So that's what I've decided to do here.
Just make sure that you don't go into the wrong clip.
So I've computed all the physics costs,
I've computed all my deltas.
I can now show what happens
If I just let the system always play the least expensive physics cost.
So now it will always play the animations and pick the minimum costs for physics.
And you could see now you get something fairly smooth.
So that's the optimal trajectory that the system can take by just checking the physics cost between all the clips.
And I do this just by saying that the next clip will be the minimum of the physics cost,
the one that has the least value.
Okay, so we know how to blend the animations, we have the physics cost and all the deltas,
we could start to play with all those real states and start to control them. So the transition
function which is this one in my case would be a bit different just because in the paper they've
took as a convention that the character when you try to put it on the path like this
They put the character as to say that they will be aligned toward x and it will walk
along the x-axis and in my case I'm used to work along z so my character is looking toward
the z-axis and is working along the z-axis so I had to switch a bunch of stuff to turn
all the mathematics to to move along z and not along x and so my formulas are
here this is how I compute so the same thing except I've changed a bunch of
stuff and so that's my transition function so what I have is I got my clip
ID I get x z and theta so clip ID x z theta that's my state that's x in the
formula here. That's x in the formula here. And the next clip ID is c prime. And that will return
the x prime. So it returned the next clip ID as x prime, z prime, and theta prime,
returning me the new state. How is the state represented? Basically, the character I would
always want it to walk along the z-axis. So a state is always represented relative to the
desired path I want to do. You can see that we never define the desired path in the informations.
The only thing we define is where my character is. It could be placed anywhere on the plane,
but that plane aims in the direction I want to walk. And basically
The theta represents how much your character is rotated relative to the desired path, so that's the theta.
And then your x and z is how offset you are compared to the center of that plane, basically.
And that's the state space, that's how it is represented in this case, right?
right? So I get my transitions to be able to transition. And now what I want to do is that I
will want to use, as a first pass, the simple policy I could have is to go through greedy policy.
And so what I will have is that I will have a direction cost. So
So how good am I walking in the direction I wanted?
And basically what we say is we know that we've,
we say that we always want to walk forward
and then we align everything relative
to where that forward is.
So what the direction cost will be
is that I'll take my X and Z.
which is my current positions, my x' z' that will be my future positions and
the only thing I make sure that I make sure that the motion itself, so that's
what you have going from here to here, the direction of the motion has to be
basically zero, the angle of that and that of that direction has to be aligned
to my z-axis, I want it to walk forward. That's what the direction cost is about.
What I would do is that because I would have animations that have a small step,
bigger steps, I'm also making sure that even if my motion is in the right
direction, I want to make sure that at least it does a step in the
right direction. So that's what I'm doing here. I check the z prime where I will be
and if that doesn't make me at least 10 centimeters steps, I multiply my cost by 3.
It's just to avoid that sometimes I will have really really really small steps but I'll
perfectly align. I will pick that one and say I will have something that start to work and then
make a really small steps. So that's where I would want the cost to be bigger. Say now I want
you to make sure that you move forward, not only that you make a really small step forward.
And what is the greedy policy? It just takes your states.
And what I would do is that I compute the transitions for all the possible different
transitions you could take. And from there, you start to compute, you try to find which
one has the least cost in total. And the different costs will be what we have here. You get the state
costs and you get the transition cost. The state cost, in my case, I would not use the second part.
I would only use the first part, which is the derivation. I want to make sure that I'm not in
in a state that deviates from where I would want to go.
So not only I want you to walk in the right directions,
but being offset, walking null in the right direction
will give you a penalty.
So that's what the deviation would give you.
It says, if you start to deviate from the trajectory,
your costs start to grow.
And that depends on how far you went.
You get the physics cost, so that's the one we pre-computed.
How well is the transition doing?
And then you get the direction cost,
is how good am I walking in the directions
I want you to walk.
And then you sum all of those costs,
and you pick the minimum cost possible.
So let's do the direction green.
Then I can take my gamepad.
And now I have this character, so the yellow arrow is where I ask the system to walk.
And so the greedy algorithm will just always check for the next clip and only for one clip.
It's like we had in a previous video, when you go for the greedy algorithm, you picked
only the what gives you the smallest error possible without taking the future into account.
And so it's not too bad but see there it just flipped and that's because
the physics cost probably I have a bunch of flipping animations that says the
the physics cost of not doing the full flip will be too high and so as soon as it starts
unfortunately to put the foot down into the flipping animations it has to keep doing the
flip and that's where I have in this case the Greedy Agony makes really bad choices
sometimes. It could keep going and do something fairly good as long as it doesn't pick that
wrong clip by mistake. But that's the greedy algorithm. And then you could choose how much
the physics matter, how much the direction matters, how much the deviation matters.
Now, of course, we've learned the greedy algorithm, but what is interesting now is to see
how to find the optimal policy. And to find the optimal policy what we have to do is again
try to figure out the cumulative cost of picking one clip relative to another one
and what you will be able to do in the future. And so what we have is that you try to minimize the
sum of all the future costs you will have.
And in this case, it could be written, of course,
as a recursive function again,
saying that my value function for x
will be equal to the cost of being in a specific state
plus the cost of picking a specific transition
plus the value functions of being into that next state.
Multiply by a factor to make sure that you can converge
and then you usually put that factor around 0.9,
0.95, something like that.
And finding the minimal, the best policy is basically,
the best policy is basically now you take the state cost and you take the
minimum of all the possible transitions you can take and basically it means
that the best policy possible is to find the minimum of the cost of the
transition cost plus the value functions. You could see that what happens is to
find the best policy, the state cost is not important anymore, only the value
functions and the transition cost is important. And that's because the state
cost itself now has been learned into the value functions. The value functions
depend on the state cost plus the future costs, which means that the policy to find the best
clip to play doesn't need to compute the state cost anymore. It's already integrated into the
value functions. And that's what you will try to learn. Last time we've done it with the Bellman
equations and recursive computations on the discrete value. We're not in a discrete world
animal, what we want to do will be to learn it on the continuous value functions.
And that's how you will do it instead of learning it step by step.
we'll have is we will have to approximate that and use a linear programming to solve the system.
So what we have to do is basically what I will want to do is that I will want to learn for
my value functions. I will try to maximize the value functions because it's a cost function.
So what I want to do is that I want to make sure that the cost will be as high as possible.
But we will set a bunch of constraints to that linear programming and the constraint will say
that my value function for a specific x needs to be smaller than the state cost for x plus the
transition cost plus the future cost. And so by doing so what happens is that you try to grow
the value functions as high as possible, but you limit the maximum size of it by the fact that
it always needs to be sure that all the different value functions between them
needs to be always smaller than the cost plus the next one. So that's because of this you've
basically turned that Bellman equation into a linear programming optimization and that's defined
the exact same properties as how we learned it in the last time. Now one of the issues is that
the value functions x here is continuous. So x can be any value of x, any value of theta,
So that value functions as a really enormous number of variable, of possible variable.
So we cannot learn it as is. We need to approximate the value functions.
And how we will approximate the value functions, we will basically go and says,
we would turn that value functions into a bunch of basis function.
because we know that the cost will be fairly smooth along all the values.
I mean if my state is at x value 1 and I'm in value 1.1 I'm fairly close to it
and I don't expect to pick an animation completely different because I'm so
close to it so all those value functions will be fairly smooth so I can approximate them with
basis functions and that's what we will do we will turn the value function of x into a bunch of
basis functions and the basis functions that will be multiplied by coefficients and what
we will have to learn now is the coefficients for all the basis functions and that's what we will
learn and keep iterating on it. So I get all my basis functions and so if I turn this problem
of maximizing vx with all those constraints, now those constraints become the value, the basis
functions of x multiplied by my coefficients needs to be smaller than the cost plus alpha the next
one. Now basically you could see that I have my basis functions on both sides. So it means that
I have to take the right hand side and put it on the left side. And so it gives me delta x minus
alpha delta x prime. It needs to be smaller than that the costs, which means that I could turn all
of this together and the alpha x minus phi x minus alpha phi x prime for the coefficients
and then I can learn the coefficients now for this one. That's how you actually turn
this problem into a linear problem you can learn. So what I would do is that I will have
my compute basis and the only thing I need to to track if I want to walk forward is how much
I've deviated from the trajectory and how is my character rotated that will impact where my clip
will go and that impact which animation I need to take so that's the the two bases I need to learn
And so I will compute those two bases that give me nine bases. It's all polynomial basis
functions. So what does it mean? It means that I have a polynomial for x. So it's one x x square.
I get a polynomial for theta, which is theta for one theta and theta square. And then because I have
two different polynomials to learn together. You basically need to do an
outer product, all of them. And so that's why you get 1 x x square theta theta x
theta x square theta square theta square theta square x theta square x square.
I'll give you all the nine bases that you're trying to learn at once. So it's
It's what they represent here.
They said that they have the polynomial.
So the simple polynomial they want to run,
that you want to learn.
And in the case of just having the task of walking forward,
that's what they said, that the polynomial of degree 2
for x and the polynomial of degree 2 for theta.
So you multiply together, that's
I mean, the other product to be able to learn all of those.
And my optimal policy now when I try to find
which one of the animation I have to play,
it's what they've defined here.
This says that if you remember,
it's this one, the arc min.
So what I do is that I take the transitions
and that gives me the physics costs
and I get the direction costs
because both of them are part of the cost of the transitions.
And that's it.
And then I compute the basis functions
of x prime and theta prime,
where I would be multiplied by coefficients
and I sum the two, so multiply by alpha.
So I get alpha plus my value functions evaluated at x prime.
And I'll take the argument of it.
And that's how you take the best clip to play.
So I get my compute basis.
I get my optimal policy.
And now, how you actually really learn this?
Normally, if you wanted to learn the value functions
and grow the value functions and do this,
One way to do it is to first, you take a bunch of samples
because, of course, it's a continuous value function.
So you can learn for all the different possibilities.
You choose a bunch of examples scattered
along all the state space.
So that's what I'm doing here.
I take a bunch of x positions between minus 2 and 2 meters.
and I take the sample theta minus, so on 360s
to rotate everything.
And I create a bunch of samples there.
So I get for each possible clip,
I will have the clip, the X somewhere
and a theta somewhere, and that give me a bunch of samples.
So that's what I have here.
All the samples I would decide to use.
So I have 900 different samples that I will learn from.
And if you wanted to do this, usually you could pre-compute all the possible transitions
between all the different states and put them all constraints at once and says, now try
to maximize your value functions with all of those.
Now it doesn't mean that in my case I will have a 900 by 900 constraint.
That's a big heavy to learn.
what the the paper decided to do is to do it iteratively so what you do is that
you start with a bunch of sets you start with a set of transition so
basically you start with the order coefficients at zero you go through all
your samples and you ask what will be the optimal transition to take
Basically, in that first case, that would be the greedy transition.
And that's the list of transitions you will have, that's the list of constraints you'll
create.
You learn the parameters and you reiterate.
You re-ask the system for all your samples, what will be now the best transition to take,
and it will be, of course, a set of different transitions.
So your L grows and you re-compute all the different constraints and you re-learn the
value functions and you iterate until you converged to something that will not add new
constraint, which is what I'm doing here.
So I will start by saying that the first thing is saying that I want to maximize the value
functions.
What I said is that take all the samples, compute the basis functions for all the samples
and that gives me my max Vx.
That's what I'm trying to maximize.
So you minimize it because you subtract it because by default linear programming we try
to minimize.
So if you try to maximize, you just need to flip the sign.
So that gives me the VX to try to maximize.
And then I go through all my samples that I've generated,
use the optimal policies
with all the coefficients I computed,
check which clip it would choose.
And if that transition does not exist already,
I'm adding that in the transition states.
And then that gives me all the transitions
want to use. And then finally, you go through all those transitions, and you start to build
the big matrix of all the coefficients. So you build the matrix of all the constraints,
this one. And so how you do it is that you compute the basis, put that on left hand, compute the
new basis for the future basis for the new theta, new x new theta, you subtract it from the alpha.
On the right-hand side, you get the cost of taking the transition plus the derivation factor,
because that's what I have here, cost of the transition plus the cost of the states plus the cost of the transitions.
That's the right-hand side.
And that gives you the matrix of all the coefficients you try to learn and all the right-hand side values.
What I do also is adding all the sample also but the inverse of them just to
make sure that basically this will mean everything needs to be smaller than the
cost and I will do the opposite saying nothing can be smaller than zero so
that's why I do the minus here just to make sure that I put a lower bound as a
cost functions cannot be negative or cannot be negative so making sure that everything is up to
zero and that's because when I would do the linear programming I would put no bounds on the values I
would let him choose the coefficients the way he wants and so I need to give him a upper bound
and lower bounds on everything he tries to learn so he gets the upper bound as maximum is the cost
plus the future and lower bound is zero. That's what you do here. There is one thing that I haven't
showed you yet is that when I do the coefficients I do have nine coefficients that's what I said
but what the paper says is that you cannot learn a value functions that will represent
all the clips plus all the bases, again, that will grow the dimensionality of what you're
trying to learn. Instead, it's that you will learn different value functions for each clip.
Each clip will have the value functions of if I'm in this clip, if you want to reach in this clip
and you reach in the in the futures with those values X theta and X prime theta prime that
will be the cost of reaching me. So you will learn it for every clip. That's what they call
tabulations. So the possibility to say that you will want to learn different values for each clip.
So I will learn different value for each clip, but I will learn everything at the same time because
I need to make sure that the value learned from one clip is reflected in the values that the other
clip points towards and that kind of stuff. So that's why I have for every clip I get the nine
bases. I compute the coefficients and I put it inside of my clip ID. I put the values for the
the compute basis and put the next clip ID, I get the minus equal alpha for the future basis
and so on. So I'm learning all the clips at once but each clips will have different values.
And so you can see that it has 3000 constraints and adding new constraints every time and learning
them and that's already gone. That's the power of having only 36 clips I would say. And being
a bit more in your future compared to the paper that we're taking around one hour to do this.
And if you want to see what we've just learned basically for the compute basis,
this is if I take the clip ID 3 this is the compute basis for it so you see
that's my x so from x to minus 2 to 2 on the x-axis and minus pi to pi on the
theta axis you could see that basically what it tells you is that it will be
really costly to arrive in the negative x with negative theta.
And it's basically less expensive to be on the positive side,
that kind of stuff.
So finds you the sweet spot of, see,
it's not even 0, 0.
The sweet spot is probably better to not be 0, 0 in this case.
So that's what the value functions, the future value
functions will give you.
And now what I could do, of course, is use exactly that.
So what I will have is, again, the same control.
And my optimal policy will use my coefficients, my future
stuff.
So I will use the same function that I use for learning.
And I got my x and theta coming from my controllers,
depending on where my character is.
And now you could see that if I walk forward,
I should never try to do that wrong flip anymore.
And I have my control, which is what
they call the near optimal control,
because you've learned for the future into a continuous matter.
You have a continuous functions.
You get a continuous control for the character
asking to walk in the right direction.
And this is it for this paper.
There is a lot of different value functions
that they learn, different basis functions that they've used
but I wanted to make sure that the basics were understood
to show how you could learn a continuous value function
and use a continuous value function instead of the discrete one.
I hope you liked it and see you next time.